<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<component>
	<content-type>/component/article</content-type>	<display-template/>
	<merge-strategy>inherit-levels</merge-strategy>
	<objectGroupId>2aad</objectGroupId>
	<objectId>2aad72b1-d5be-c4e4-42c3-7a3312e0929a</objectId>
	<file-name>4-film-series-to-catch-in-n-y-c--this-weekend.xml</file-name>
	<folder-name/>
	<internal-name>4 Film Series to Catch in N.Y.C. This Weekend</internal-name>
	<title>4 Film Series to Catch in N.Y.C. This Weekend</title>
	<featured_b>true</featured_b>
	<featuredImage>/static-assets/item/articles/en/2019/05/17listings-movies-superJumbo.jpg</featuredImage>
	<thumbnailImage>/static-assets/item/articles/en/2019/05/17listings-movies-superJumbo.jpg</thumbnailImage>
	<articleTeaser/>
	<articleBody>&lt;p&gt;By Ben Kenigsberg&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;May 16, 2019&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our guide to film series and special screenings happening this weekend and in the week ahead. All our movie reviews are at nytimes.com/reviews/movies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AN ALL-COLORED VITAPHONE SHOW at Film Forum (May 20, 6:20 p.m.). Instead of combining film frames with an optical soundtrack, Vitaphone, an early sound system, synchronized the moving image with a record. This program highlights a variety of shorts made with the system that were showcases for African-American artists, including Duke Ellington, Cab Calloway and Ethel Waters. The following week, on May 28, Film Forum will host a tribute to Ron Hutchinson, who died in February; he was a founder of the Vitaphone Project, a campaign to restore Vitaphone films.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;212-727-8110, filmforum.org&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DELANYMANIA at the Metrograph (May 17-19). The science fiction author Samuel R. Delany wrote the notes for this series, which consists of movies he saw early in life and considers to be influences. He was taken with the anti-ostracism moral of Joseph Losey&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;The Boy With Green Hair&amp;rdquo; (on Saturday and Sunday), for instance, because it spoke to the otherness he felt growing up gay. He remembers that &amp;ldquo;The Seventh Seal&amp;rdquo; (on Saturday) marked the end of his &amp;ldquo;paired moviegoing&amp;rdquo; with his father, &amp;ldquo;or any further appreciation on his part of why I liked movies or why I would want to occasionally make them,&amp;rdquo; Delany said in press materials. Also showing: a program of his own films (on Saturday), Jean Cocteau&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Orpheus&amp;rdquo; (on Sunday) and Orson Welles&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Touch of Evil&amp;rdquo; (on Sunday).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;212-660-0312, metrograph.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ADVERTISEMENT&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Read about the events that our other critics have chosen for the week ahead.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EMOTIONAL TIME: THE FILMS OF HENRY JAGLOM at Spectacle Theater (through May 30). Jaglom, a gadflylike figure in the late career of Orson Welles, has spent more than four decades directing his own independent passion projects. His stature with critics may be shaky, but this program makes the case that there is artistry in his solipsism. The series leans heavily on the films he made in the 1980s, including &amp;ldquo;Can She Bake a Cherry Pie?&amp;rdquo; (on Tuesday and May 28); &amp;ldquo;Someone to Love,&amp;rdquo; which was Welles&amp;rsquo;s last film as an actor (on Wednesday); and &amp;ldquo;New Year&amp;rsquo;s Day&amp;rdquo; (on May 26).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;spectacletheater.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FIGHTING MAD: GERMAN GENRE FILMS FROM THE MARGINS at the Quad Cinema (May 17-23). The German filmmaker Dominik Graf (&amp;ldquo;Beloved Sisters&amp;rdquo;) co-directed a documentary called &amp;ldquo;Doomed Love: A Journey Through German Genre Film,&amp;rdquo; screening on Saturday and Wednesday, which presents what the Quad describes as an &amp;ldquo;alternative history&amp;rdquo; of 1960s and &amp;rsquo;70s West German genre cinema &amp;mdash; interesting films that aren&amp;rsquo;t helmed by such widely acclaimed directors as Herzog, Fassbinder or Wenders. Graf also co-programmed this series, designed to satisfy anyone whose appetite is whetted by his documentary. The series goes beyond the doc&amp;rsquo;s time frame, but among the offerings from that period are the true-crime thriller &amp;ldquo;Bloody Friday&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;Blutiger Freitag&amp;rdquo;), on Friday and Monday, and &amp;ldquo;Dead Pigeon on Beethoven Street,&amp;rdquo; an often inscrutable tongue-in-cheek mystery made by the American Samuel Fuller for West German TV, on Saturday and Wednesday. The film features, in heavy rotation, Can&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Vitamin C,&amp;rdquo; later used to accompany similarly baffling proceedings in &amp;ldquo;Inherent Vice.&amp;rdquo; A companion series on Graf&amp;rsquo;s own films will play at Anthology Film Archives May 24 through June 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;212-255-2243, quadcinema.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Editors&amp;rsquo; Picks&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the High-Flying Hamptons, Real Estate Is in a Rut&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From &amp;lsquo;Smallville&amp;rsquo; to a Sex Cult: The Fall of the Actress Allison Mack&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A New Mom, Her Nannies and the Often Exploitive Labor of Motherhood&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A version of this article appears in print on May 17, 2019, on Page C24 of the New York edition with the headline: Film Series. Order Reprints | Today&amp;rsquo;s Paper | Subscribe&lt;/p&gt;</articleBody>
	<createdDate>2019-05-17T18:02:39.793Z</createdDate>
	<createdDate_dt>2019-05-17T18:02:39.793Z</createdDate_dt>
	<lastModifiedDate>2019-05-17T18:05:10.050Z</lastModifiedDate>
	<lastModifiedDate_dt>2019-05-17T18:05:10.050Z</lastModifiedDate_dt>
	<postedDate_dt>2019-05-17T04:00:00.000Z</postedDate_dt>
</component>